Canada's Population

Before reading more about Canada and the Canadian people, consider what you already know. If you haven’t been to Canada, do you already have an idea about who Canadians are based on what you have heard or seen? Do you think of the country in stereotypes, such as "The citizens don’t like Americans," or "Everyone speaks French"?

Firecrackers explode, and a giant dragon's head bobs through the crowded streets as the Chinese New Year erupts in the Pacific port city of Vancouver. Some 500 mi. (800 km.) to the east, cowboys round up a herd of Alberta Angus for winter dehorning. In Ottawa, Ontario, the prime minister addresses Parliament, while in nearby Montreal, the lilting sounds of Québecois French fill a smoky bistro. Off the coast of Nova Scotia, rugged fishermen pull in their nets for the day, and 1,000 mi. (1,600 km.) to the north, giggling Inuit schoolchildren whistle at the dancing aurora lights as they play in the midday darkness. These are just a few snapshots from a day in the life of Canada and its people.

Canada is second only to Russia in sheer physical size. It spans more than 3,850,000 sq. mi. (9,971,500 sq. km.) and crosses six time zones. It contains fully one-third of all the freshwater on Earth, with shores on three oceans and the longest coastline of any nation. A bilingual country of distinct French and English cultures, Canada has long been a haven for immigrants. Today, this nation also celebrates its native peoples, most especially the Inuit (Eskimo). The Inuit now control their own northern homeland within the Canadian federation—Nunavut. North American Indians, Canada's First Nations, form by far the largest population group in the Northwest Territories.

Canada encompasses more than 5 percent of Earth's landmass. Yet it is home to fewer than 0.5 percent of the world's people. Of these, more than 80 percent live in a 100-mi. (160-km.)-wide ribbon along Canada's southern border with the United States. Indeed, the people and economies of these two North American nations have long been intimately tied.

Like the United States, Canada is a democratically governed federation of states. Specifically, it has 10 provinces and 3 territories. Canadians elect representatives to a parliamentary government. The political party in control of the Parliament selects a prime minister to head the government.

THE LAND

Canada encompasses nearly half the North American continent. It stretches from the northern tip of Ellesmere Island—some 1,150 mi. (1,850 km.) north of the Arctic Circle—to Lake Erie's Middle Island (a point south of 15 U.S. states). Canada is bounded on the north by the Arctic Ocean, on the west by the Pacific, and on the east by the Atlantic. There are four geologically distinct land regions. They are the Appalachian Highlands, the Canadian Shield, the Interior Lowlands and Plains, and the Western Cordillera.

The massive Canadian Shield covers more than one-half of the country's land area. It includes most of Quebec, Ontario, Nunavut, and the Northwest Territories. Eons of glacial activity have ground down the 2-billion-year-old mountains that formed the shield, leaving a vast, saucer-shaped basin, with the enormous Hudson Bay at its center. The eastern edges of the shield tilt up at Baffin Island and Labrador, where glaciers still cover dramatic mountain peaks, and sheer cliffs drop abruptly into the Atlantic Ocean.

South of Labrador, the ancient, worn-down mountains of the Appalachian Highlands rim the southeastern edge of the Canadian Shield. This is the northern finale of the Appalachian mountain system that begins in the southeastern United States. Canada's Appalachia is most rugged in Quebec's Gaspé Peninsula. There, peaks rise to more than 4,000 ft. (1,220 m.) in the Shickshock Mountains. The landscape smooths out in the Atlantic Provinces to form rough plateaus, hills, valleys, and a coastline indented with many bays, inlets, and harbors.

To the south of the Canadian Shield, the land drops to form the fertile lowlands of the Great Lakes and St. Lawrence River Valley. To the west, these lowlands broaden into the Interior Plains. They stretch across the Prairie Provinces of Manitoba, Saskatchewan, and Alberta, and reach up into the western Northwest Territories.

West of the Great Plains lies Canada's Western Cordillera. It is a region of high mountain ranges interspersed with valleys. On the Cordillera's eastern edge, the Rocky Mountains extend up from the United States. They trace the border of Alberta and British Columbia, and reach into the Yukon and Northwest Territories, where they become the Mackenzie Mountains.

Along the Pacific are British Columbia's scenic Coast Mountains. They rise abruptly from the ocean to heights of nearly 10,000 ft. (3,000 m.). The western coastal ranges also include the chain of partly submerged peaks that form Vancouver Island and Haida Gwaii (formerly Queen Charlotte Islands). In the Yukon, the coastal ranges become the St. Elias Mountains, with Canada's highest peak, Mount Logan (19,525 ft.; 5,951 m.), near the border with Alaska. Nestled between the Rockies and the Coast Mountains lie many smaller mountain chains and plateaus, and the fertile fruit-growing region of the Okanagan Valley.

In addition to these four major land regions, Canada's Arctic Archipelago encompasses a small but unique band of volcanic, sedimentary, and metamorphic rocks. Folded in different directions at various times in geologic history, they form the glacier-covered hills and mountains of the Queen Elizabeth Islands. They rise most dramatically on Ellesmere Island, with glacier-capped peaks nearly 8,000 ft. (2,400 m.) high. Cape Columbia on Ellesmere Island is Canada's northernmost point.

Climate

Canada's populated southern region experiences a wide range of temperate climates. Its Pacific coast enjoys the warming effect of the North Pacific Drift (Japan Current). The drift keeps Vancouver's average winter temperatures above freezing. Pacific breezes cool West Coast summers. Seasonal temperature swings become more dramatic on the inland prairies and provinces. There, the long, cold winters average 0° to 16° F. (−18° to −9° C.) in January, and short, warm summers average 66° to 72° F. (19° to 22° C.) in July.

The climate becomes somewhat milder again in the Atlantic Provinces. The northern half of Canada experiences a subarctic and Arctic climate. Average temperatures are well below freezing for nine to ten months of the year. Summer temperatures north of the Arctic Circle, although generally cool, can spike to as high as 100° F. (38° C.).

Rain falls abundantly along Canada's East and West Coasts. The western slopes of British Columbia's Coast Mountains receive the most, making this one of the world's largest cool-weather rain forests. Throughout the northwest and Canada's eastern provinces, generous rainfall and the rugged landscape combine to produce some mighty rivers, which power a number of hydroelectric dams. By contrast, agriculture in the arid central prairie depends heavily on irrigation.

In the late 20th century, much of eastern Canada's rain contained pollutants that came primarily from U.S. factories and power plants. A major program was then developed to curb the resulting "acid rain" that damaged forests and lakes. The program helped to ease tensions over this issue between the two nations.

WEALTH OF THE LAND

Canada is one of the world's richest nations in terms of its natural resources. Primary among this great wealth are its minerals, timber, and waterpower. Woodlands cover some 40 percent of the land. Most of this forest produces timber ideal for lumber, pulp, and paper. Indeed, Canada is the world's largest producer of newspaper thanks to the vast stands of softwood trees in its eastern provinces. The towering hardwood forests of British Columbia produce most of the nation's quality lumber.

Canada's many large rivers and waterfalls make hydroelectric power an important source of energy. The nation's largest hydroelectric plants fuel many energy-intensive industries, such as aluminum smelting. But these colossal dams remain controversial. This is because of the environmental damage they cause to rivers, their fish life, and the lands that surround them.

Fur and fish are the natural resources that first led to Canada's exploration and settlement. They remain important local industries along the country's coastlines and among its native people.

Plant and Animal Life

Except for tiny Prince Edward Island, all of Canada's provinces and territories encompass expanses of virtually unpopulated wilderness. In such an environment, wildlife can appear to be an inexhaustible resource. History has taught Canadians differently: uncontrolled hunting, damming, and logging have driven species such as whales, sea otters, and bison to the brink of extinction, and harmed habitats such as the delicate Arctic tundra and the Pacific coastal rain forest.

Canada has three major types of plant habitat: forests, grasslands, and tundra. In the east, Canadian forests tend to be mixed woodlands filled with deciduous trees such as sugar maple and beech, and coniferous trees such as pine and hemlock. These eastern forests support a varied assortment of animal life, including white-tailed deer, squirrels, mink, and skunks. The dense spruce forests of the north and the towering cool rain forests of the far west provide habitats for many distinctly Canadian animals such as moose, beavers, wolves, and Canada lynx, as well as grizzlies and black bears.

Most of the prairie grasses that once carpeted Canada's interior plains have been plowed under for farmland. The hundreds of thousands of bison that once ranged here have been reduced to a few protected herds. Other surviving wildlife includes coyotes, gophers, badgers, and jackrabbits.

Stunted tundra vegetation covers Canada's northern quarter, where the permanently frozen soil, or permafrost, prevents tree growth. Spongy carpets of moss and lichen and tufts of sedges and grass dominate the landscape, accented by a profusion of wildflowers in spring. Tundra land mammals are few but distinctive. They include the polar bear, musk ox, caribou, and lemming. Summer brings enormous flocks of migrating birds.

THE PEOPLE

The native people of Canada include the Athabascan tribes of western Canada; the Algonquian tribes of eastern Canada; the Déné of the Pacific Northwest; and the Inuit of the Arctic. With the arrival of Europeans, Canada's native people became valued partners in the European fur trade. A great blending of cultures created a new one—the Métis, or people of "mixed race."

Missionaries largely destroyed the distinctive culture of the Déné people of Canada's Pacific Northwest. But in the last quarter of the 20th century, the Tlingit, Haida, and other Déné tribes worked to save their languages from extinction. They also resumed the long-forbidden gift-giving potlatch ceremony and the carving of traditional sculptures on masks, totem poles, houses, and boats.

Canada's Inuit population lives mainly in Canada's Arctic and subarctic. In 1999, they took charge of the newly created, self-governing territory of Nunavut. It had been carved out of the existing Northwest Territories.

Overall, there is mounting pride in their heritage among Canada's native peoples. Coupled with a high birth rate, this has led to a large increase in the number of people describing themselves as belonging to one of Canada's native groups. In the 2006 census, Métis, First Nations, and Inuit constituted 4 percent of the total Canadian population—a 45 percent increase since 1996. Most live in or near cities.

Canada's population of 35 million is roughly one-fourth British in ancestry, one-fourth French, and one-third other ethnicities. Among them are other Europeans (15 percent); native people (2 percent); other, mostly Asian, African, Arab people (6 percent); and those of mixed background (26 percent). In 1969, the Canadian Parliament passed the Official Languages Act. It established a bilingual nation in which all government and legal transactions would be conducted in both French and English. Nearly 60 percent of Canadians speak English; about 22 percent speak French.

Canada's English-speaking population lives throughout the country. British customs and traditions remain strongest in British Columbia, Ontario, and the Atlantic Provinces. French Canadians maintain their distinct culture most strongly in the province of Quebec. Many descendants of the Acadians, the original French-speaking settlers of "New France," live in Nova Scotia and other parts of the Atlantic Provinces.

The population of Canada increased dramatically in the second half of the 20th century, thanks in large part to immigration. Before the 1970s, the vast majority of immigrants came from nations within the British Empire (and its successor organization, the Commonwealth of Nations), Europe, and the United States. Since then, Canada has drawn many immigrants from Asia, India, and the West Indies. Canada also maintains an open door for political and humanitarian refugees of all nations.

Some 43 percent of Canadians, including most French-speaking communities, consider themselves Roman Catholic. Another 23 percent are Protestant. The United Church of Canada and the Anglican Church make up the largest Protestant faiths. About 2 percent of the population is Muslim.

The Canadian way of life is influenced by the United States. In fact, about 80 percent of Canadians live within 125 mi. (200 km.) of the U.S. border. Billions of dollars in goods, services, and investments cross the U.S.-Canadian border each year. This exchange has worked to the benefit of both nations.

CITIES

Until the early 1900s, most Canadians lived on farms or in small villages. Today, almost half live in the country's six largest cities of Toronto, Montreal, Ottawa, Vancouver, Edmonton, and Calgary.

Toronto

Toronto is Canada's largest city and its most important economic center. It is located on the northwest shore of Lake Ontario and is also the capital of the province of Ontario. The name "Toronto," of Huron origin, is usually translated "place of meeting." Toronto was first settled by people from Great Britain and Ireland. In 1951, 73 percent of the city's population was of British origin, but by 1991, this figure had declined to 19 percent. During the 1950s, immigrants came from Italy, Germany, Greece, and Portugal. By the 1970s, they were coming from the Caribbean, the Indian subcontinent, and Hong Kong. Toronto became the most culturally diverse city in the country.

Toronto is the country's financial and manufacturing center. Canada's largest stock exchange is located there, as well as the headquarters of banks and insurance companies. Among Toronto's educational institutions are the University of Toronto, York University, and Ryerson University. The most visible place of interest is the CN (Canadian National) Tower, one of the world's tallest freestanding structures.

Toronto's Royal Ontario Museum, one of Canada's largest, is renowned for its Chinese collection. The Art Gallery of Ontario has the world's largest collection of sculptures by Henry Moore. Toronto is the home of the Canadian Opera Company and the National Ballet of Canada. Roy Thomson Hall is a glamorous showcase for the Toronto Symphony Orchestra. The city's waterfront offers sailing schools, theaters, and arts and crafts galleries. Ontario Place includes marinas, Adventure Island, an open-air theater, and the Cinesphere, which houses a six-storey-high IMAX motion picture screen.

Montreal

Montreal is located on an island in the middle of the St. Lawrence River. It is the largest city in the province of Quebec, the second-largest city in Canada, and one of the world's largest inland seaports. The city of Montreal covers most of Montreal Island and has spread eastward onto the mainland. Two-thirds of its residents are French-speaking. Montreal is the second-largest French-language city in the world after Paris.

Because of its location on the St. Lawrence River, Montreal is one of Canada's leading ports. It is also a financial center. Many of the great insurance and banking firms in Canada have their headquarters in the city. Montreal has several universities. McGill and Concordia are English-language institutions. McGill is well known for its medical school. The Université de Montréal and Université de Québec conduct classes in French.

Many tourists from North America come to Montreal. The charm of the city comes from the blending of its French and English cultures. Many tourists visit the Notre-Dame Basilica. Other places of interest include Saint Joseph's Oratory, the Marché Bonsecours, and lovely Dominion Square. The Montreal Museum of Fine Arts has a superb collection of paintings. The Musée d'Art Contemporain de Montréal exhibits the work of modern artists. The Place des Arts is the home of the Montreal Symphony Orchestra.

Ottawa

Ottawa is the capital of Canada. It is located on the Ottawa River, about 125 mi. west of Montreal. The name "Ottawa" comes from the Algonkian word "adawe," which means "to trade." Fur-trading posts were built along the Ottawa River before 1800 because it was an important route for the Montreal fur trade. The first permanent European settlement in the Ottawa River valley was Wright's Town, now the city of Gatineau, Quebec.

Ottawa became the nation's capital because of rivalry among the cities of the Province of Canada. The Province of Canada was formed in 1841 by the union of Upper Canada and Lower Canada. However, no one could agree on a site for a capital. For 20 years, the role of capital passed, in turn, among Kingston, Montreal, Toronto, and Quebec City. To end the argument, Queen Victoria of England was asked to pick a permanent site. In 1857, she chose Ottawa, the most central city, as a compromise between a French Canadian and an English Canadian location.

The people who live in Ottawa are mostly of British origin. Other ethnic groups are French and Irish. The federal government is the city's largest employer. The tourism and convention industry is the second-largest employer. Manufacturing has declined since the beginning of the 1900s, but a major computer technology industry has developed.

The National Gallery of Canada in Ottawa displays Canadian art and art from other countries. The Canadian Museum of Civilization is located across the river in Gatineau, Quebec. In Ottawa are Library and Archives Canada and the Royal Canadian Mint. The National Arts Centre attracts international and North American performers. The University of Ottawa is Canada's oldest and largest bilingual university.

Vancouver

Vancouver is the largest city in the province of British Columbia and Canada's third-largest city. It is located on the coast of southwestern British Columbia. Its magnificent harbor is the second largest in Canada and one of the busiest on the Pacific coast of North America. Its spectacular setting and moderate climate make it one of Canada's most attractive cities. The city is named for George Vancouver. He explored Canada's western coast at the end of the 1700s.

The first permanent European settlement was established in the 1860s. Vancouver was settled mainly by people of British origin, as was the rest of British Columbia. Today, people of British background make up the largest population group. People of Asian background now make up more than a quarter of the city's population.

The University of British Columbia and Simon Fraser University are located in the Vancouver metropolitan area. The Vancouver Art Gallery is known for its collection of Emily Carr paintings. The Orpheum Theatre is home to the Vancouver Symphony Orchestra. Stanley Park is a vast forest with stands of virgin timber. Vancouver hosted the Winter Olympic Games in 2010.

ECONOMY

In colonial times, fur trapping, fishing, and logging were Canada's primary industries. Today, the service industries make up the largest segment of the economy, followed by manufacturing, construction, and mining. Canada enjoys a modern, well-developed economy with a high standard of living. Its provincial and territorial governments provide free or low-cost health insurance for all legal residents. Canada ranks higher than the United States in life expectancy. It boasts one of the world's best telecommunication systems. For this and other reasons, the United Nations (UN) has traditionally ranked Canada high on its "human-development index."

Services

Service industries account for more than 75 percent of the country's gross domestic product, or GDP. (GDP is the total value of goods and services produced in a year.) Community, business, and personal services, which include tourism, make up the largest and fastest-growing segment of the economy. Other services contributing to GDP are finance, insurance, and real estate; wholesale and retail trade; transportation, communication, and utilities; and government, which includes education and health care.

Manufacturing

Canada's vast natural resources provide the raw materials used to manufacture countless products. One leading manufacturing segment is transportation equipment. It includes automobiles, trucks, railroad locomotives, and aircraft. Another is processed foods, particularly meat and fish products. Other important industries produce petroleum, natural gas, and chemicals; processed minerals; and wood and paper products.

Agriculture and Fishing

Ninety percent of Canada's produce comes from the Great Lakes–St. Lawrence Lowlands and the Prairie Provinces. Other fertile areas are located in the lowlands of the Maritime Provinces and in the river valleys of British Columbia. Important grain crops, especially wheat and canola, are grown on the prairies. The wheat belt extends from northeastern British Columbia, through Alberta and southern Saskatchewan and into southwestern Manitoba. Saskatchewan is the leading wheat-producing province. Many grain crops are grown to provide feed for livestock. Irrigated crops are produced on the dry fringes of the wheat belt. These include alfalfa, sugar beets, potatoes, peas, beans, and lentils.

Livestock—dairy and beef cattle, sheep, hogs, and poultry—earn more income for the individual Canadian farmer than the sale of grain. The most important dairy-farming areas are in the Great Lakes–St. Lawrence Lowlands and in the lower Fraser River valley of British Columbia. The southern parts of Manitoba, Quebec, Alberta, and Ontario are important hog-producing areas. The Great Lakes–St. Lawrence Lowlands and the southern interior of British Columbia are the chief fruit- and vegetable-growing centers. Prince Edward Island is known as Canada's garden province. It is the country's major potato-growing area.

Two of the world's most productive fishing grounds lie off Canada's East and West coasts. One of these—off the southeastern shores of Newfoundland—is the famous Grand Banks. It has been an important fishing area since the early 1600s. However, overfishing has caused a virtual elimination of cod and a tremendous decline of haddock, pollock, and halibut.

The coastal waters off British Columbia and the inlets of the Inside Passage are famous for salmon, halibut, and shellfish. Salmon is the most valuable fish in the Pacific fisheries. But its numbers are also declining due to overfishing and the development of hydroelectric power projects along the Columbia River. The decline of the salmon and lobster populations in the Atlantic is also reaching crisis levels. Consequently, aquaculture (fish farming) has become a growing industry.

Canada's inland lakes yield great numbers of freshwater fish. These include trout, whitefish, walleye, perch, sturgeon, pike, and many others. All together, about 3 billion lb. (1.35 billion kg.) of fish and shellfish are taken from Canadian coastal and inland waters every year.

Canada has taken steps to protect its fishing industry from foreign competition. In 1976, it established a limit of 200 nautical mi. (370 km.) off its coasts. Other protective measures are being considered as Canada works toward rebuilding its depleted fish stocks.

Mining

The nation's mineral wealth has long been a major force in its economy. Canada is among the world's leading producers of nickel, zinc, and diamonds. And it is a major producer of uranium, platinum, cobalt, gold, aluminum, and lead. Vast deposits of crude oil and natural gas have been tapped beneath Canada's Great Plains. The Athabasca oil sands of Alberta contain the world's largest known oil reserves. But the process of removing the tarry oils from the sands remains expensive. It is also a significant source of air pollution.

Energy

Canada has a great wealth of energy resources. More than 70 percent of the country's total energy production comes from petroleum and natural gas. Historically, coal was the primary source of energy in Canada. However, its importance has diminished due to developments in nuclear and hydroelectric power.

Trade

Canada's primary trading partner is the United States. It is the largest foreign supplier of oil, natural gas, uranium, and electric power to the United States. Canada's other major exports include motor vehicles and parts, industrial machinery, aircraft, and telecommunications equipment; chemicals, plastics, and fertilizers; and wood pulp and timber. Some 75 percent of Canada's exports go to the United States. More than 50 percent of Canada's imports come from the United States.

In 1994, Canada, the United States, and Mexico officially adopted the North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA). This measure has helped to increase trade among all three countries by eliminating barriers to trade, including, for example, taxes on imported goods.

Transportation

Considering Canada's enormous size and relatively small population, the country's transportation systems are remarkable. Canada has two transcontinental railway systems, the Canadian Pacific Railway and the Canadian National Railways. Their chief function is to move freight, particularly manufactured goods and coal, grain, and potash.

Passenger service is provided by VIA Rail. It offers service to some 450 communities from coast to coast. There are, in addition, some 50 regional, or shortline, rails that branch out from the main lines. In total, Canada's rail systems form a network covering more than 50,000 mi. (80,000 km.).

More than 540,000 mi. (870,000 km.) of roads stretch from the Atlantic to the Pacific and from southern Ontario to Alaska. The most notable is the Trans-Canada Highway. It extends from St. John's, Newfoundland, to Victoria, British Columbia. This is a distance of approximately 4,800 mi. (7,700 km.). Canada's vast network of roadways continues to be improved and expanded. This is done in part to accommodate the rapid expansion of the trucking industry.

Ports and Waterways

Every year, more than 100,000 vessels sail in and out of Canada's 300 commercial ports and harbors. Montreal, Halifax, St. John, and Quebec City are the main Atlantic ports. Vancouver is situated on an inlet of the Pacific Ocean. It is Canada's busiest port. Another major Pacific port is Prince Rupert.

The St. Lawrence Seaway connects the Great Lakes and the Atlantic Ocean. It allows oceangoing vessels to enter ports in Toronto, Hamilton, Sault Ste. Marie, and Thunder Bay on the Great Lakes. From April through December when it is ice-free, the seaway makes it possible for these inland ports to engage in direct overseas trade.

Communication

Despite long distances between settled areas, Canadians are closely linked by telephone, the Internet, radio, and television. There are some 150 television stations. Satellite and cable systems provide access to a wide range of stations including those of the United States. There is also a mix of public and commercial radio broadcasters. The Canadian Broadcasting Corporation (CBC), the public radio broadcaster, operates four radio networks, Radio Canada International, and radio services to native populations in the north.

Some 20 major daily newspapers are published in major cities. They serve both the English- and French-speaking communities. A number of newspapers also appear in other languages. Toronto alone publishes more than 100 newspapers for ethnic communities. Canada has more than 27 million Internet users.

CULTURE

Architecture

Early architecture in Canada was designed by the country's native people. The buildings included the longhouse, wigwam, tipi, pit house, plank house, and igloo. The homes were adapted to the lifestyle and environment of the people who lived in them. The buildings of the early European settlements followed the style of architecture used in Europe. The first structures of New France were military. They were built in the French baroque style. The two most common building types during this period were the homestead and the parish church, however. The churches were built in the French Gothic and baroque styles. Homes were built in the rural French style but modified for the climate of New France. The roofs were built at a steep angle to allow snow and ice to easily slide off, for example.

After Canada became a British colony, the style of architecture changed to the English style. The Loyalists who came from the United States were fond of the Georgian style. It represented their loyalty to King George. The medieval Gothic style was used for churches and public buildings. This is the style of Canada's Parliament buildings. The grand railway hotels, such as the Château Frontenac in Quebec City, were a uniquely Canadian form of architecture.

Canadian architects from the late 1900s to today are admired all over the world for their innovative and creative designs. They include Douglas Cardinal, Arthur Erickson, Frank Gehry, and Moshe Safdie.

Art

Rock carvings and paintings are the oldest surviving examples of art by Canada's native people. Among the most dramatic forms are the carved totem poles of the Northwest Coast First Nations. The oldest examples of Inuit art are carvings from bone, ivory, or antler. Today, the Inuit carve soapstone and ivory. Early artists of New France were mostly French-born clergymen who specialized in religious works. They decorated local churches with paintings and wooden sculptures in the baroque style. By the mid-1700s, merchants in Montreal and Quebec City were wealthy enough to purchase works of art. This created a small market for portraits and landscape paintings.

Sculpture in the British colonial period was also decorative works carved out of wood. Many of the painters were British officers stationed throughout eastern Canada. They showed the Canadian landscape in detailed watercolor paintings. The works of two artists from the mid-1800s are landmarks of Canadian art. Paul Kane traveled across the country recording the lifestyle of Canada's native people in sketches and paintings. Cornelius Krieghoff is best known for his scenes of life in rural Quebec. Later landscape artists such as Lucius O'Brien and John Arthur Fraser celebrated Canada's dramatic natural features.

A close connection with Europe continued until the early 1900s. Many of the best painters of the time, including Paul Peel, Robert Harris, and William Brymner, trained in Paris. They returned to introduce Canadians to various current styles, such as impressionism and postimpressionism. James Wilson Morrice and Horatio Walker gained international reputations. Painting in the 1920s was dominated by the Toronto-based artists known as the Group of Seven. They were dedicated to producing a truly nationalist art. They concentrated on painting Canada's rugged northern wilderness. Important contributions were also made by Tom Thomson, whose landscapes inspired the Group of Seven, and Emily Carr and David Milne.

Music and Dance

Music in Canada has its earliest roots in the drumming and dancing traditions of the country's native people. Fiddles and fifes were popular instruments of the early French and British settlers. Musicians who received formal musical training were generally church musicians. As Canada grew in size and population, musical societies formed and concerts were held regularly. Montreal had a symphony orchestra as early as 1845. Quebec City has the oldest continuously active symphony orchestra.

Dance in Canada has a history similar to that of music. The earliest dancers were the country's native people. When the French and British settlers arrived, they brought their folk dances with them. Folk dancing of all traditions is still performed across Canada.

Canada has many ballet and modern dance companies. The National Ballet of Canada is the country's largest dance company. It makes its home in Toronto but performs throughout the world. The Royal Winnipeg Ballet, founded in 1939, is Canada's oldest dance company.

Theater

The National Theatre School of Canada, founded in Montreal in 1960, conducts classes in both French and English. Students receive professional training in acting, directing, stage production, and stage design. Montreal is the major center of French Canadian theater. The largest centers of English-speaking theater are Montreal, Toronto, and Vancouver, although most major cities in Canada have at least one theater company.

Leading Canadian stage actors include Colleen Dewhurst, Martha Henry, William Hutt, Kate Nelligan, Christopher Plummer, Kate Reid, and Colm Feore. In 1953, the Stratford Shakespeare Festival opened in Stratford, Ontario. Several other Canadian cities hold annual Shakespeare festivals every summer. In 1962, the Shaw Festival opened in Niagara-on-the-Lake, near Niagara Falls, Ontario. It features the plays of the dramatist George Bernard Shaw. The largest fringe festival in North America has been held annually in Edmonton, Alberta, since 1982.

Literature

Canadian writers have a worldwide audience. Canadian literature is written in English and French. French-language writing, centered in Quebec, has thrived along with the literature of the English language. The earliest examples of Canadian literature were journals written by explorers, traders, and others who settled the Canadian wilderness. Their writings describe the land and the hardships and rewards of pioneer life. The literary works of the early 1800s also focused on the land and on life in the pioneer settlements and growing towns. Susanna Moodie moved to Canada from England in 1832. Her autobiographical book Roughing It in the Bush (1852) is an account of the pioneer experience.

The poets Charles G. D. Roberts, Bliss Carman, Archibald Lampman, and Duncan Campbell Scot captured the beauty and variety of the Canadian landscape. Their work became well known in the 1880s and 1890s. Among the most important fictional works of the period were the animal stories of Roberts and Ernest Thompson Seton. Other writers of this period used Canada's small villages and towns as the settings for their books. This technique is called "regionalism." Two early regional writers were Ralph Connor and Lucy Maud Montgomery. Montgomery's popular first novel was Anne of Green Gables (1908).

French Canadian fiction continued the traditions of the romantic rural novel. It usually depicted the peaceful life of the small Quebec village. One example is La Terre paternelle (translated as The Homestead) by Patrice Lacombe, published in 1846. Two novels that portrayed life in the city rather than in small villages marked the beginning of modern Quebec literature. Au pied de la pente douce (1944; translated as The Town Below) by Roger Lemelin was set in one of Quebec City's poor sections. Bonheur d'occasion (1945; translated as The Tin Flute) by Gabrielle Roy took place in a poor neighborhood of Montreal.

English Canadian fiction entered the modern period with The Double Hook (1959) by Sheila Watson. Much fiction, poetry, and drama in both English and French was published in the 1960s. The major writer of the decade was Margaret Laurence. Five of her novels were set in the fictional prairie town of Manawaka. Michel Tremblay was a playwright, fiction writer, and translator. He focused on the working class of Quebec cities. Roch Carrier, Marie-Claire Blais, and Nicole Brossard are other important writers from Quebec.

Modern English Canadian literature is dominated by Margaret Atwood. Her works present the Canadian individual confronting the modern world. Atwood has many contemporaries. Robert Kroetsch's fiction and poetry explore the Canadian West. Alice Munro is noted for her short stories of rural life. And Michael Ondaatje's works portray the disorder of contemporary life.

HISTORY

Like all of North America, the land that is now Canada was first populated by hunters who crossed the Bering Sea from Asia by the end of the last Ice Age, some 10,000 years ago. The first evidence of permanent settlements in the Canadian Arctic dates to about A.D. 4,000. In A.D. 1000, the Viking explorer Leif Ericson landed on the shores of what is now Newfoundland, nearly 500 years before Columbus. In 1497, John Cabot claimed "New Found Land" and its rich offshore fisheries for England. In 1534, the French explorer Jacques Cartier reached the Gulf of St. Lawrence and claimed the surrounding land for France. The Huron-Iroquois people Cartier met called their homeland Kanata, meaning "village" or "community." The French dubbed it "New France," and began a lucrative trade in furs. In 1603, Samuel de Champlain explored and mapped much of New France, leading to the first permanent European settlements.

Over the next century, the Iroquois, Hurons, and other native peoples battled alongside the traders and settlers of different European nations as they each struggled to take control of the vast, fur-rich territory. In 1759, the British defeated the French. Four years later France relinquished its claims. Although the British expelled thousands of French Acadians from the Atlantic Provinces, the inland French were largely unaffected.

In 1774, Britain granted the French people of Quebec the right to pursue their own legal and religious customs. American colonists to the south protested this act as favoring French Catholics. They listed it among the Intolerable Acts that ignited the Revolutionary War. The Americans tried unsuccessfully to take the city of Quebec in 1775. When Britain finally recognized U.S. independence in 1783, some 40,000 British Loyalists fled to Canada. They greatly enlarged its English-speaking population.

The late 1700s and early 1800s were a time of great exploration in the Canadian Northwest. British explorer Sir Alexander Mackenzie forged river routes to the Arctic and Pacific Oceans. The Hudson's Bay Company and North West Company financed additional expeditions and many settlements.

By the mid-19th century, Canada had become the great "North Star" for African Americans fleeing slavery via the Underground Railroad. Some 30,000 runaway slaves gained freedom this way between 1840 and 1860. Between 1861 and 1865, some 40,000 to 50,000 Canadians crossed the border to fight in the American Civil War.

In 1867, the British Parliament peacefully recognized Canada as an independent nation with the right to self-government. But not all Canadians welcomed being "turned over" to the new government. The Métis leader Louis Riel led a French-Canadian movement demanding a separate territory within the new nation. The uprisings led to Riel's execution.

In 1926, Britain recognized the constituents of its empire, including Canada, as free and equal partners in what became the Commonwealth of Nations. When World War II broke out in 1939, Canada rallied to Britain's side, and Canadian troops participated in major operations, including the D-Day invasion in 1944. The postwar years brought economic prosperity to Canada, with the discovery of bountiful deposits of oil, natural gas, uranium, and iron.

The 1960s saw the birth of a separatist movement in Quebec. Many Québecois demanded that their province form its own French-speaking nation. In 1968, Prime Minister Pierre Trudeau championed the vision of a bilingual and bicultural country. And in 1980 and 1995, the people of Quebec defeated referenda for independence. In 1982, a new and truly Canadian Constitution went into effect. This removed the last remnant of the British government's power in North American government, although Canada still retained its symbolic ties to the British monarchy.

In 1991, Prime Minister Brian Mulroney unveiled a reform program that included the creation of Nunavut, which became a reality in 1999. In 1993, Kim Campbell became the first woman to serve as Canada's prime minister. In December 2003, Paul Martin succeeded Liberal Party leader Jean Chrétien, who had been prime minister since November 1993. Martin remained head of a minority government after the 2003 elections. But he was ousted in a no-confidence vote in November 2005.

After new elections were held in January 2006, Conservative leader Stephen Harper replaced Martin as prime minister. Harper retained his post as head of a minority government after October 2008 and January 2009 elections. Forced to hold new elections in May 2011, Harper gained support. He formed a majority government.

In October 2014, Canada joined the U.S.-led campaign of air strikes against the terrorist group that calls itself the Islamic State in Iraq and Syria, or ISIS, in the Middle East. Later the same month, it found itself the target of terrorist attacks at home. A Canadian convert to Islam drove his car into a group of soldiers in Quebec. He killed one of them and was himself shot and killed by the police. Two days later, on Parliament Hill in Ottawa, another Muslim convert shot and killed a soldier. He then attacked the Parliament building, where he was shot and killed. The government responded with beefed-up security measures and new anti-terror legislation.

In October 2015, Canada's Liberal Party returned to power in a sweeping electoral victory. The party was led by 43-year-old Justin Trudeau, who became prime minister. He is the son of former prime minister Pierre Trudeau.



Tone

Tone can represent many things, from the soothing tones of music, to the tone of speech an adult uses when he or she praises or reprimands you. In a literary work, tone is defined as the attitude an author toward his or her subject. Tone can be represented by the choice or use of words (diction), images, or even rhythms used in poetry or speeches.

Tone and Emotional Content Transcript
NARRATOR 1: Now, sometimes when we read poetry, we get general feelings about them. They may seem uplifting or humorous, or maybe sad or ominous. And there’s another word for that idea. Tone. To get more specific, let's see if you can define it. 
A video shows a woman, the narrator, speaking directly to the camera.
NARRATOR 2: In poetry, we define tone as (clock ticking): A. the pitch of the poet’s voice; B. the highest parts of the stressed syllables; C. the repetitive sounds of end rhymes; or D. the emotional coloring or attitude of the work.
Text reads: D, The emotional coloring or attitude of the work 
NARRATOR 3: Tone is the emotional coloring of a poem. So you could have a happy poem or a sad poem. You could have an angry poem. For example, Edgar Allen Poe’s work is very dark and brooding. 
A video shows a middle-aged woman outside speaking directly to the camera.
NARRATOR 2: Once upon a midnight dreary, while I pondered, weak and weary, 
Over many a quaint and curious volume of forgotten lore— 
While I nodded, nearly napping, suddenly there came a tapping,
As of some one gently rapping, rapping at my chamber door.
A man’s voice is heard reading the passage on the screen. Faded Images in the background show a quill pen and a black bird.
Text reads: From “The Raven” by Edgar Allan Poe.



